--- PAGE 1 ---
Sensor Placement and Selection
for Bearing Sensors with Bounded Uncertainty
Pratap Tokekar and Volkan Isler
Abstract—We study the problem of placing bearing sensors measuring bearing corrupted by unknown but
sensors so as to estimate the location of a target in a bounded noise. Bounded noise models provide a useful
square environment. We consider sensors with unknown
alternative to probabilistic models especially when a
but bounded noise: the true location of the target is
precisedevicemodelisnotavailable(perhapsduetothe
guaranteed to be in a 2α-wedge around the measurement,
where α is the maximum noise. The quality of the place- difficulty of calibration or changing device parameters).
ment is given by the area or diameter of the intersection Suchmodelshavelongbeenusedforstateestimation[2]
of measurements from all sensors in the worst-case (i.e. and for sensor fusion in robotics applications [7].
regardlessofthetarget’slocation).Westudythebi-criteria
Asanexample,consideranapplicationwheresensors
optimizationproblemofplacingasmallnumberofsensors
are deployed to be used as beacons for localizing a
whileguaranteeingaworst-caseboundontheuncertainty.
navigating robot (Figure 1). At each time instant, the
Our main result is a constant-factor approximation:
We show that in general when α ≤ π, at most 9n∗ robot can query the sensor network for their bearing
4
sensorsplacedonatriangulargridhasdiameterandarea measurements towards the robot. In the bounded uncer-
uncertainty of at most 5.88U D ∗ and 7.76U A ∗ respectively, tainty model, the true bearing to the robot is guaranteed
wheren∗,U D ∗ andU A ∗ arethenumberofsensors,diameter to lie in a 2D wedge which is centered at the measured
andareauncertaintyofanoptimalalgorithm.Inobtaining
bearing and has an apex angle equal to the maximum
these results, we present some structural properties which
may be of independent interest. We also show that in sensing noise. Measurements from multiple sensors are
the triangular grid placement, only a constant number combinedbyintersectingthecorrespondingwedges.The
of sensors need to be activated to achieve the desired uncertainty in the robot’s estimate is usually taken to be
uncertainty, a property that can be used for designing
the diameter or area of the intersection. We seek worst-
energy/bandwidth efficient sensor selection schemes.
case quality guarantees for our estimate: Given the true
I. INTRODUCTION location of the robot, imagine an adversary choosing
the noise values for sensors. The true location can be
Sensor placement for target localization is a funda-
anywhere in the intersection and we would like this set
mentalprobleminroboticsandsensornetworks.Agood
to be “small” no matter where the robot is.
placement scheme can improve the performance of sen-
sornetworksinapplicationssuchasintruderdetectionin
surveillance, robot navigation using exteroceptive mea-
surements,andprovidinglocationinformationtomobile
devices for location-aware computing – a technology
identified as key for the advancement of robotics [3].
Most sensors employed for localization have a strong
structureassociatedwiththeirsensingmodel.Thisstruc- Fig.1:Here,theareaofintersectionforasquaregrid1(middle)
ture plays a critical role in how information from multi- and random placement (right), for the true robot location
plesensorscanbecombined.Inthispaper,westudythe (marked by triangle), is 1.32 and 3.27 times that of the
triangular placement (left). In this paper, we derive the rela-
sensorplacementproblemforbearingsensorswhichare
tionshipbetweenthetriangulargridparametersandworst-case
commonly used in robotic and networked sensor sys-
uncertainty,andshowthatthenumberofsensorsrequiredare
tems: monocular cameras, microphone/acoustic arrays, near optimal.
directional radio antennas, passive infrared receivers,
etc., all measure bearing towards a target. We consider
We consider a simple workspace for the problem:
The target can lie anywhere within a square without
The authors are with the Department of Computer Science and
anyobstaclesorvisibilityconstraints.Eveninthisbasic
Engineering, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, USA.
{tokekar,isler}@cs.umn.edu setting, devising a sensor placement scheme is tricky. It
--- PAGE 2 ---
is intuitively clear that the optimal placement should be is visible from at least two sensors and their relative
some kind of a uniform grid. However it is not clear angle lies within a desired interval. They presented a
if the grid should be square, triangular or some other log factor approximation, up to a fine discretization.
shape. Further, optimizing parameters of the grid (e.g.
In addition to the relative angles, the uncertainty is
resolution) is not straightforward because as illustrated
also affected by the distance between the sensors and
in Figure 1, the estimate is obtained by combining
the target. Geometric Dilution of Precision (GDOP)
measurements from all sensors. This makes it difficult
is one measure relating the uncertainty with distance
to express its area or diameter in closed-form in order
and relative angles. Tekdas and Isler [12] presented a
to optimize grid parameters. While there have been
placement scheme which guarantees that for any target
attempts to find the optimal solution [14], the problem
location there are always two sensors whose GDOP is
of optimal placement for bearing sensors remains open.
a constant factor of the GDOP achieved by any two
In this paper, we make progress towards solving sensors from an optimal placement. We do not restrict
this fundamental problem. We focus on placement on the estimator to use only two sensors, instead, allow
a triangular grid and derive the relationship between combiningallmeasurements.Ercanetal.[6]studiedthe
uncertainty and grid resolution. We prove that the num- problem of placing horizontal scan-line cameras along
ber of sensors required to achieve a desired uncertainty the boundary of a circular room to minimize least-
is only a constant times that of an optimal algorithm. squares localization error for a target with a given prior.
Furthermore for a triangular grid, only a constant num- Their placement result shows that a uniform placement
ber of sensors can be queried to obtain performance along the boundary is optimal. We allow sensors to be
comparable to querying all sensors. This implies for placed anywhere within a square workspace, without
our motivating example, the robot may query only a assuming any prior for the target’s location.
fixednumberofnearbysensorstolocalizeitselfwithout
Isler and Magdon-Ismail [9] considered the problem
losing much estimation quality.
of selecting a small subset of sensors from a given
The rest of the paper is organized as follows: We
placement;eachsensor’soutputisaconvexsubsetofthe
begin by presenting the related work in Section II. We
plane. They proved that irrespective of the total number
describe the sensing model and formalize the problem
ofsensors,thereisalwaysasubsetoffourmeasurements
in Section III. The analysis for lower bounds for an
that can be selected, which when combined yield an
optimal placement, and upper bounds for a triangular
intersection area at most twice of that obtained by
grid placement is presented in Sections IV and V.
intersecting all measurements. In their problem, the
Complete proofs for the analysis are presented in the
placement of the sensors and the actual sensor mea-
accompanying technical report [13]. We conclude with
surements are already given. For the same placement of
a discussion of our results in Section VI.
sensors, this subset would change if the measurement
changes. This poses an interesting question whether
II. RELATEDWORK
there is some placement of sensors for which the same
The problem of optimizing the placement of sen-
subsetcanbeusedtoapproximatetheuncertaintyregion
sor nodes has received significant attention from the
for different (but perhaps “nearby”) measurements. In
sensor networks community [15]. A large amount of
this paper, we present a result in this direction for
research has focused on self-localization of networks,
bearing measurements with bounded noise.
forexampleinthecaseofmobile,reconfigurablesensor
Bounded uncertainty models have previously been
networks [8] and for stationary sensor networks with
used in robotics problems. Detweiler et al. [4] and
reference anchor nodes [1]. In our present work, we
Spletzer and Taylor [11] studied the problem of self-
assume that the locations of the sensors themselves
localization in passive beacon fields and robot networks
are accurately known and focus on the complementary
respectively,usingsensorsyieldingboundeduncertainty
problem of placing sensors so as to localize targets.
measurements. Song and O’Kane [10] studied the prob-
For bearing sensors, the uncertainty in target’s es-
lem of maintaining approximation for robot’s possible
timate depends on the relative position of the sensors
locations obtained by intersecting pre-images from sen-
and the target. Motivated by this, Efrat et al. [5] studied
sors yielding measurements with bounded noise. Set
the problem of minimizing the number of sensors to be
membership estimation [2] is an estimator designed for
placedinapolygon,suchthateachpointinthepolygon
sensorsyieldingunknownbutboundednoise,whichhas
been applied for robot localization using bearing mea-
1We randomly place additional sensors to the square grid, so that
ithasthesamenumberofsensorsasthetriangulargrid. surements [7]. We describe our bounded noise sensing
2
--- PAGE 3 ---
s s
and uncertainty model in the next section. 3 4
III. PROBLEMFORMULATION
In this section, we first describe the notation, define s 2
s
the sensing and estimation models, and use them to 1
formulate the problem studied in this paper.
A. Notation and Sensing Model
Fig.3:Twoestimatesforthesamesensorsandtargetlocation,
but different measurements resulting in different uncertainty.
We use worst-case intersection as the uncertainty measure.
si 2 x set of measurements to maximize the uncertainty in
the target estimate. We use two measures (area and
diameter2 of Pˆ) to define the uncertainty. The diameter
Fig.2:Theactualmeasurementθi mliesanywherebetweenθi t ± uncertainty of a placement S is defined as:
α
is
.
g
θ
u
i t
a
i
r
s
an
th
te
e
ed
tru
to
eb
co
ea
n
r
t
i
a
n
in
g.
t
T
he
he
tr
w
ue
ed
ta
g
r
e
ge
fo
t
r
lo
a
c
g
at
i
i
v
o
e
n
n
x
m
.
easurement UD(S),m
x
ax
θm
ma
θ
x
(x)
diameter(Pˆ(S,θ m )), (1)
∈A ∈
The workspace is a d d square. The target’s true where θ(x) is the set of valid measurements that can
locationxcanbea A nywhere × within .Considerasensor be obtained from S for a target location x. The area
A uncertainty can be similarly defined.
placementS = s
1
,...,sn whereeachsi denotes
{ } ∈A
the sensor location. Each sensor measures the bearing
towards the target as θ
i
m =θ
i
t+ni, where θ
i
t [0,2π) C. Objective
∈
is the true bearing (Figure 2). ni [ α,+α] is the Broadly, there are two factors that affect the worst-
∈ −
bounded sensor noise. α is the bound on the absolute case uncertainty: (i) the number of sensors, and (ii) the
noise in the sensor. The pre-image of a measurement location of placed sensors. In this work, we take the
θ
i
m is a 2D wedge (denoted by W(si,θ
i
m)) as shown in approachthattheuserspecifiesadesireduncertaintyand
Figure 2. This wedge is not the same as a fixed field- the objective is to minimize the number of sensors and
of-view sensor; for the same target location, the sensor find the corresponding placement to guarantee that the
can receive any sensing wedge of angular width 2α so worst-caseuncertaintyisbelowtheuser-specifiedvalue.
long as it contains the true target location. In particular, we address the following problem:
The target estimate obtained by combining a set of Find the minimum number of sensors required and
measurements θm = [θm,...,θm]T from n sensors, thecorresponding placement toachieve adesireddiam-
1 n
is defined as the intersection of the n sensing wedges eter uncertainty U (or area uncertainty U ).
D∗ A∗
W(si,θ
i
m). That is, Pˆ(S,θm), n
i=1
W(si,θ
i
m). Here Our main result shows that by placing sensors on a
Pˆ is a convex polygonal region wThich can possibly be triangular grid-like placement, 9 times as many sensors
unbounded. as an optimal algorithm are sufficient to guarantee 5.88
timesthedesireddiameteruncertainty(respectively,7.76
B. Adversarial Formulation of Uncertainty
times the area uncertainty) when the maximum sensing
The size of Pˆ depends on the actual measurements. noise is less than π.
Figure 3showstwoinstanceswherethesizeofPˆ differs Theorem 1: Let 4 the maximum absolute noise for
significantly for different measurements obtained from bearing sensors be 0 < α π. Let the desired
thesameplacementofsensors.Theactualmeasurements diameter uncertainty for a d ≤ d s 4 quare environment
obtainedbythesensorscannotbecontrolledbytheuser. be U < d (respective × ly, area uncertainty be
D∗ 7sinα
However, we will show that by carefully placing the U < πsin2α d2). If an optimal placement algorithm
sensors one can guarantee there always exists a good A∗ 196
achieves U (respectively, U ) with n sensors, then a
D∗ A∗ ∗
set of valid measurements.
triangular grid-like placement achieves at most 5.88U
D∗
We model the objective using an adversarial process:
Given a placement of sensors, an adversary selects a
2The diameter of a polygon is the length of the largest segment
target location within the square and a corresponding containedcompletelywithinthepolygon.
3
--- PAGE 4 ---
(respectively,atmost7.76U )withatmost9n sensors. S of n bearing sensors, then the diameter uncer-
A∗ ∗
tainty is bounded as UD(S) 2rsinα (respectively,
The analysis for Theorem 1 is based on covering a UA(S) πr2sin2α). ≥
≥
d d square with equilateral triangles of sensors. When To prove Lemma 2, we show that when the target
×
the desired uncertainty is higher than the restriction in lies at the center of C and each sensor receives a
Theorem 1 and comparable to the size of , an optimal measurementequaltothetruebearing,acircleofradius
A
placementmayuseveryfewsensors.Nevertheless,even rsinα centered at the target lies completely within the
forthatcasethetotalnumberofsensorsforthegrid-like intersection of all sensing wedges. This instance gives a
placement is bounded (given by Lemma 6). lower bound for the worst-case uncertainty.
In the following sections, we analyze the number of When a desired uncertainty is given, we can apply
sensors required for an optimal algorithm and for a Lemma 2 to find the radius of the largest such circle
triangular grid-like placement. In this paper, we state lyingintheworkspace andnotcontaininganysensor.
A
the key lemmas and sketch their proofs. The full proofs Corollary 1: LetS beanoptimalplacementachiev-
∗
areincludedintheaccompanyingtechnicalreport[13]. ingadesireddiameteruncertaintyU (respectively,area
D∗
uncertaintyU )inasquareworkspaceofsided.Ifr is
A∗ ∗
IV. LOWERBOUNDSFOROPTIMALPLACEMENT the radius of the largest circle lying completely within
and not containing any sensor in its interior, then
In this section, we first present lower bounds on the A
uncertainty achieved by any placement of sensors in the r ∗ ≤ 2 U si D n ∗ α (respectively, r ∗ ≤q U π A∗ sin 1 α ).
plane. We apply this to bound the number of sensors Corollary 1 implies an upper bound on how far each
placed within by an optimal algorithm. point in can be from any sensor or the boundary
First consid A er the case when the maximum sensing of . Th A is allows us to bound the number of sensors
A
noise α π, i.e., the sensing wedges are at least half- required for an optimal algorithm as a function of r ∗ .
planes.W ≥ e 2 showthattheadversarycanalwayschoosea Corollary 2 states that Ω( d r2 2 ) sensors are needed to
valid measurement set for any placement, such that the guarantee coverage of a d d area.
×
sensing wedges have an unbounded intersection. Corollary 2: Letr ∗ betheradiusofthelargestcircle
Lemma 1: For any placement S of n bearing sensors within a square of side d, not containing any sensor
with maximum absolute noise α π, there exists a from an optimal placement in its interior. If the desired
measurement set θm such that the ≥ in 2 tersection of the diameter uncertainty is U D∗ < dsinα (respectively,
w ca e n L d e g b m e e s m ( a a T s 1 n i= l i a 1 m r W g p e li ( e s a s i s , t θ h i m at , )) w i. i h e s . e , u n n U α b A ou ≥ (S nd ) π 2 ed = t . he Θ un ( c d e 2 r ) tai a n n ty d U op A∗ t W im < h a e l n d a d 2 lg π o s r i 4 i n 2 t 2 h r α m ∗ , ) t n h th ∗ e e ≥ d n es t ( h i d r − e π e r d 2 n ∗ r 2 u ∗ u ) n m 2 c . b e e rt r ai o n f ty se is ns c o o r m s p f a o r r ab a l n e
A ≤
UD(S)=Θ(d) for any placement of sensors, including to , and the optimal algorithm would place very few
A
theoptimal.Theproofisbasedonconstructingasimple sensors, yielding a trivial lower bound. The bound on
instance when α= π, i.e., the sensing wedges are half- the uncertainty implies that d > 2r is an interesting
2 ∗
planes. We create a measurement set where the lines case: If d > 2r , then there is a smaller square within
∗
corresponding to all half-planes pass through the target where all points are more than r away from the
∗
A
location.Weassigndirectionstoallhalf-planestoensure boundary and hence require at least one sensor within
that their intersection is unbounded. r .Wecanshowthatthesetofcirclesofradiir drawn
∗ ∗
Lemma 1 is not surprising, since α π corresponds abouteachsensorintheoptimalplacement,shouldform
≥ 2
toveryhighnoise.Inpractice,bearingsensorsaremuch a cover of this smaller square, yielding the bound.
more accurate. For the rest of the paper, we only focus
on the case when the maximum sensing noise α< π. V. PERFORMANCEOFTHETRIANGULARGRID
2
Inthefollowing, wewilllower bound theuncertainty Next, we analyze the number of sensors required
for any placement parametrized by the distance of the and the uncertainty for a triangular grid-like placement.
target to the closest sensor. Recall from Equation 1, While for lower bounds it sufficed to consider specific
the uncertainty is defined as the max over all possible instances, upper bounds require considering all possible
target locations, and all valid measurements. Hence, for target locations and sets of measurements.
a lower bound, it is sufficient to consider a particular
A. Uncertainty with Triangular Grid
targetlocationandvalidmeasurementset,asgivennext.
Lemma 2: If there exists a circle C with radius r Before the main analysis, first consider two special
which doesn’t contain any sensor from a placement configurations of sensors: (i) three sensors placed on
4
--- PAGE 5 ---
theverticesofanequilateraltriangle s s s withside
1 2 3
r, when 0 < α < π, and (ii) six △ sensors placed on s 1 s2 r
the vertices of a reg 6 ular hexagon when π α s1 r e
π. For case (i), the target may lie anywh 6 ere ≤ withi ≤ n a
4
s s s (Figure 4(a)). We further divide the analysis
s6 s3
△
into
1
in
2
te
3
rvals based on α, given next.
s3 r s2
Lemma 3: Let s s s be an equilateral triangle of
s5 s4
1 2 3
△ (a) (b)
sider withabearingsensorplacedateachvertex.Ifthe
target lies within s 1 s 2 s 3 and S = s 1 ,s 2 ,s 3 then Fig. 4: (a) Based on α, we upper bound the uncertainty
△ { }
π when the target lies within an equilateral triangle or a circle
11.35rsinα 0<α< ,
18 containedwithinaregularhexagonofsensors.(b)Wepadthe
 π π
UD(S)
≤ 
2.
1
04
+
r
1 r 1 π 8 ≤
α
α
<
< π 12
,
i
t
s
hr
e
e
n
e
c
r
l
e
o
g
se
io
d
ns
by
w
a
it
n
h
e
a
q
d
u
d
i
i
l
t
a
io
te
n
r
a
a
l
l
s
tr
e
i
n
a
s
n
o
g
r
l
s
e
t
o
o
f
e
s
n
e
s
n
u
s
r
o
e
rs
a
.
nypointinA
(cid:16) √3 (cid:17) 12 ≤ 6
and,

2ǫ then (k2) sensors placed on a triangular grid are
23.46r2sin2α 0<α< π , O
18 sufficient for bounded intersection of sensing wedges
UA(S) √3r2 +10.1(rsinα)2 π α< π , when the target lies within a circle of radius r .
≤
3√
4
3r2
1
π
8 ≤
α<
1
π
2
.
√3
4 12 ≤ 6 B. Number of Sensors with Triangular Grid

The proof partitions the triangle into three regions, and Lemma 3 gives an upper bound on the uncertainty
assigns sensors for each region such that any valid for a placement of sensors in , if there exists an
A
set of measurements results in bounded intersection. equilateral triangle of sensors enclosing any point in .
A
The sensing wedges corresponding to each partition are Sincethesensorscannotbeplacedoutsideof ,regions
A
approximated to bound their intersection. near the boundary of may not have an enclosing
A
When α π, the sensing wedges become too large equilateral triangle if sensors are placed only on a
to result in b ≥ ou 6 nded intersection with just three sensors. triangular grid. The three regions where this occurs are
Instead we use six sensors, placed on a regular hexagon marked 1 , 2 , 3 in Figure 4(b). We place additional
A A A
with center o and side r, to bound their intersection. sensors within these regions to ensure that any point
The target can lie anywhere within a circle of radius in is enclosed by an equilateral triangle of sensors.
r centered at o. We find an upper bound to the Lem A ma 6 states that ( d r2 2 ) sensors are sufficient to
√3 O
uncertainty, by finding the intersection of the union of cover a square of area d d.
×
all sensing wedges for each sensor, corresponding to all Lemma 6 (Upper Bound on Number of Sensors): If
target locations within the circle. wr = d/r +1,,wc = d/√3r +1,br = (d r )/r ,
⌊ ⌋ − 2
Lemma 4: Lets ...s bearegularhexagonofsider d √3r (cid:4) (cid:5) (cid:4) (cid:5)
1 6 bc = − 2 +1 are the number of sensors in odd
andcenterowithabearingsensorplacedateachvertex, (cid:22) √3r (cid:23)
and maximum absolute noise π α π. If the target and even rows and columns, respectively of a
lies inside a circle of radius r6 ≤ cente ≤ red 4 at o then, triangular grid with side r in a square of side d, then
√3 wrwc +brbc +3(2wr +br)+8 sensors are sufficient
UD( s
1
,...,s
6
) r sin2α+3.76sinα+1.232 to cover the square with equilateral triangles of side r.
{ } ≤
(cid:0) (cid:1) The lower and upper bounds obtained can be ap-
and, UA( s
1
,...,s
6
) 1.5rUD( s
1
,...,s
6
.
{ } ≤ { } plied to get the main result of this paper: Recall from
Lemma 4 bounds the intersection when the sensing
wedges are at most a quadrant (α π), and the target Corollary 1, that an optimal algorithm has to place
l w ie h s en wi s t e h n in sin a g c w ir e c d le ge o s f a r r a e di a u t s le √ a r s 3 t . a L ≤ e h m a 4 l m f-p a la 1 ne sh ( o α ws th π a ) t , r a sensor U A∗ wit 1 hin ) o d f is e t v an er c y e p r o ∗ int ≤ t 2 o U si e D n ∗ n α sur ( e eq th u e iva d l e e s n ir tl e y d ,
theresultingintersectioncanbeunboundedinthew ≥ or 2 st- u ∗ nc ≤ ert q ain π ty. si F n o α r the triangular g A rid placement, set the
c w a i s t e h .W 0 e < can ǫ, e t x o ten b d ou th n e d re th s e ult n i u n m L b e e m r m o a f 4 se f n o s r o α rs = pl π a 2 c − ed ǫ grid length as r = 2 U si D n ∗ α (respectively, r = q U π A∗ sin 1 α ).
Hence, r r. Corollary 2 gives a lower bound on
∗
on a triangular grid, sufficient to guarantee that the ≤
thenumberofsensorsrequiredforanoptimalalgorithm
intersection of all wedges is bounded.
in terms of r , and Lemma 6 gives an upper bound
∗
Lemma 5: Let the maximum absolute sensing noise
for the grid-like placement in terms of r. Lemma 3
be α = π 2 − ǫ with 0 < ǫ. If sin− 1 (cid:16) √ 1 3k (cid:17) + 6(k π − 1) < and Lemma 4 bound the uncertainty of the grid-like
5
--- PAGE 6 ---
placement in terms of r. Using r r and substituting questionwepursueinourfuturework.Futureworkalso
∗
≤
the value of r, the result in Theorem 1 can be obtained. includesaddressingsensinglimitationssuchasvisibility
The upper bounds from Lemma 3 and Lemma 4 constraints and placement in complex environments.
reveal that only a small number of sensors in our
ACKNOWLEDGEMENT
placement suffice to achieve an uncertainty comparable
tothatobtainedbycombiningallmeasurements.Thisis This material is based upon work supported by the
useful when there is prior knowledge about the target NationalScienceFoundationunderGrantNos.1111638,
location (e.g. a subset of ) and only those sensors 0916209, 0917676, 0936710.
A
correspondingtotheenclosingtriangleorhexagonneed
REFERENCES
be queried for their measurements.
Corollary 3: Givenatargetlocationxwithinasquare [1] F.Benbadis,K.Obraczka,J.Corte´s,andA.Brandwajn. Explor-
ing landmark placement strategies for topology-based localiza-
and desired diameter uncertainty U (respectively, area
D∗ tioninwirelesssensornetworks.EURASIPJournalonAdvances
uncertainty U A∗ ), if sensors are placed on a triangular inSignalProcessing,2008:138,2008.
t g h r r i e d e w s i e th ns s o i r d s e a r re = su 2 f U s fi i D n ∗ c α ien (r t e w sp h e e c n tiv 0 el < y, r α = < qπ U π A∗ an s d in 1 α si ) x , [2] D s o e n . t- A B m u e e t r m o ts m b e a e k r t a i s s c hi a C p n o d d n e t I r s . o c l r R , ip h 1 t o 6 io d ( n 2 e ) s : o . 1 f 1 R 7 u – e n c 1 c u 2 e r r 8 s t , a iv i 1 n e 9 ty 7 s . 1 ta . t I e EE es E tim Tr a a ti n o s n ac f t o io r n a s
sensors are sufficient when π α π to ens 6 ure diam- [3] R.D’Andrea. Guesteditorial:Arevolutioninthewarehouse:a
6 ≤ ≤ 4 retrospective on Kiva systems and the grand challenges ahead.
eter uncertainty at most 5.88U D∗ (respectively, 7.76U A∗ ). IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering,
9(4):638–639,2012.
Corollary 3providesasensorselectionmethodwhich [4] C.Detweiler,J.Leonard,D.Rus,andS.Teller. Passivemobile
robot localization within a fixed beacon field. Algorithmic
may be useful in sensor network applications with
FoundationofRoboticsVII,pages425–440,2008.
energy or bandwidth constraints that require activating [5] A. Efrat, S. Har-Peled, and J. Mitchell. Approximation algo-
only a small number of sensors. rithms for two optimal location problems in sensor networks.
In2ndInternationalConferenceonBroadbandNetworks,pages
VI. CONCLUDINGREMARKS 714–723.IEEE,2005.
[6] A. Ercan, D. Yang, A. El Gamal, and L. Guibas. Optimal
In this paper, we studied a placement problem for placement and selection of camera network nodes for target
bearing sensors. We used a bounded uncertainty formu- localization. In International Conference on Distributed Com-
putinginSensorSystems,pages389–404.Springer,2006.
lation which allowed us to represent each measurement
[7] A.GarulliandA.Vicino.Setmembershiplocalizationofmobile
as a wedge containing the target’s location. The quality robotsviaanglemeasurements. IEEETransactionsonRobotics
of the estimated target location was quantified by the andAutomation,17(4):450–463,2001.
[8] L. Hu and D. Evans. Localization for mobile sensor networks.
diameter or the area of the intersection of wedges. In
In Proceedings of the 10th annual international conference on
this setting, a fundamental question that arises is: What Mobilecomputingandnetworking,pages45–57.ACM,2004.
is the minimum number and placement of sensors that [9] V. Isler and M. Magdon-Ismail. Sensor selection in arbitrary
dimensions. IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and
guaranteesthatnomatterwherethetargetis,orwhatthe
Engineering,5(4):651–660,2008.
actual measurements are, the uncertainty in the estimate [10] Y. Song and J. M. O’Kane. Comparison of constrained geo-
is below a desired level? metricapproximationstrategiesforplanarinformationstates. In
Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Robotics
This basic question turned out to be surprisingly
andAutomation,2012.
hard due to the fact that the quality of the estimation [11] J. Spletzer and C. Taylor. A bounded uncertainty approach
dependsonthelocationsofallsensorsaswellastheac- to multi-robot localization. In Proceedings of the IEEE/RSJ
International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems,
tual measurements. Our results provided insights about
volume2,pages1258–1265,2003.
the structure of this problem and yielded a placement [12] O. Tekdas and V. Isler. Sensor placement for triangulation-
scheme with constant-factor approximation guarantees. based localization. IEEE Transactions on Automation Science
andEngineering,7(3):681–685,2010.
In particular, we showed that unless the sensor noise is
[13] P. Tokekar and V. Isler. Sensor placement and selection for
too large, a placement of sensors on a triangular grid bearing sensors with bounded uncertainty. Technical Report
yields a good performance. Further, (excluding some 12-006, Department of Computer Science & Engineering,
University of Minnesota, February 2012. http://www.
extreme cases) we showed that for the triangular grid
cs.umn.edu/research/technical_reports.php?
placement, if a rough estimate of the target location is page=report&report_id=12-006.
available, one can obtain a good estimate by querying [14] E.Yfantis,G.Flatman,andJ.Behar. Efficiencyofkrigingesti-
mationforsquare,triangular,andhexagonalgrids.Mathematical
only a fixed number of sensors. This latter sensor
Geology,19(3):183–205,1987.
selection scheme is particularly appealing for resource [15] M. Younis and K. Akkaya. Strategies and techniques for node
constrained sensor-network applications. placement in wireless sensor networks: A survey. Ad Hoc
Networks,6(4):621–655,2008.
Can this result be improved, perhaps by showing
that the triangular placement is optimal? This is a
6
