--- PAGE 1 ---
Cautious Greedy Strategy for Bearing-based Active Localization:
Experiments and Theoretical Analysis
Joshua Vander Hook, Pratap Tokekar, Volkan Isler
Abstract—We study the problem of minimizing the time to
accurately localize a target using radio-based telemetry. The
directional nature of the antenna allows us to obtain bearing-
to-targetsensormeasurements.Therearetwocriticalattributes
that seperate our setup from the majority of bearing-only
tracking literature: ambiguity and long measurement time.
We provide a sensing strategy which midigates the effect of
ambiguity,andprovethatthetimerequiredtolocalizeatarget
is less than a constant times any bearing-based localization
strategy.
I. INTRODUCTION
Inactivelocalization,theobjectiveistoplanmeasurement
locations for a mobile robot so as to accurately localize a
target. In most applications, the true location of the target is
unknown. Instead, the robot must estimate the target’s loca-
tionfromitsmeasurements.Theprimarysourceofdifficulty
in active localization problems is their online nature: With
eachmeasurement,therobotobtainsmoreinformationabout
the target’s location which should be incorporated into the
choice of future measurement locations. The online nature
of the decision making process makes it difficult to provide
Fig.1. Themobilerobot,loopantenna,andsensingequipment.Thepicture
theoretical guarantees about the performance of an active
wastakenduringfieldtrialsonLakeGervais,MN.
localization algorithm.
The motivating application for our study is localizing
radio-taggedinvasivefishinlakes.Inthissetting,severalfish a bearing measurement. During this time the robot must
are caught and surgically implanted with low-power radio remain stationary to avoid changing the range or bearing
transmitters. The tagged fish are released, and eventually to the target. Our objective is to find a series of discrete
associate with larger groups. During the winter months, measurements which provide a good final estimate of the
the majority of a lake’s population tends to aggregate and target location. We seek to minimize the time taken to
remain stationary. By tracking the radio-tagged fish, which localize the target for two reasons: (i) We would like to
eventually join these aggregations, the population can be minimize the probability that the target moves during the
foundandtargetedforremoval[1].Sincemanualmonitoring measurement process, and (ii) to possibly track multiple
of tagged fish is time-consuming and potentially dangerous targets. Similar objectives have been studied in the context
in harsh conditions, we are developing a robotic system to ofbearings-onlylocalization,butthelongmeasurementtime
continuously monitor tagged fish. Our ultimate goal is to andambiguityofthissensingmodalitysetthisproblemapart
monitor many fish in a lake to detect aggregations. fromthemajorityoftheliteratureonbearings-onlytracking.
Ourplatform,showninFigure1,iscomposedofamobile The infinite-line sensor was considered by [2], in the con-
robot and a directional antenna mounted on a servo motor. text of pursuit-evasion games. A finite-time capture strategy
By rotating the antenna and finding the direction with the was provided by using pairs of measurements to resolve
strongest signal strength, one can compute a line that passes the ambiguity. But with sensor noise, this strategy cannot
through the robot and the radio tag. The exact bearing is guarantee capture, because large measurement noise makes
unknown due to the symmetric nature of the antenna. For it increasingly difficult to resolve the true bearing (See [3]
this reason, we refer to this type of sensor as an infinite-line for more detail).
sensor. Since the radio tags transmit with a low duty cycle This problem has been considered in the wireless sensor
(less than 1 Hz), it can take up to one minute to construct network community, since direction of arrival, and therefore
abearingmeasurement,canbeestimatedfromreceivedradio
The authors are with the Department of Computer Science and
messages (see [4] for a high-level survey). Ultimately, these
Engineering, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, USA.
{jvander,tokekar,isler}@cs.umn.edu works solve a fundamentally different problem and cannot
--- PAGE 2 ---
provide sensing locations to minimize the resulting error.
Similarly, Derenick et al. [5] considered radio-based bearing
measurements in the context of cooperative localization for zˆ
teams of mobile robots. However, the robots were consid- α i
ered to be arbitrarily moving, and no motion strategy was
provided. z⋆ xˆ
s
Disregarding ambiguity, the problem of tracking a ma- x⋆ i
neuvering target using bearing-only measurements has been
G
well studied (e.g., [6]–[8]). The main focus of this thread of
literature is on optimizing an estimator to be robust when
provided arbitrary input. Fewer results exist for structur- s F h ig o . w 2 n . .xˆ T i h is e t s h e e ns c o u r rr l e o n c t a t t a io rg n e , t s h i y i p s o d th e e sc si r s ib . e T d he by pr r e i di = cte | d |xˆ m − ea s s i u | r | e a m n e d n α ts i a a re s
ing the input itself, i.e., designing an optimal sequence of shownaszˆ i (grayline),andtheactualnoiselessmeasurementisgivenby
discrete measurements. Some relevant results are [9], who z⋆ (dashedline).
provided an action-space search which used the determinant
of the posterior covariance as a utility function and [10],
who numerically calculated an optimal approach using the the ith measurement. The prior target estimate is a 2-D
Fischer Information Matrix (FIM). These results are useful Gaussian distribution given by (xˆ ,Σ ). The mean and
0 0
N
for approximating an optimal continuous trajectory, but are the covariance of the estimate after the ith measurement are
designed for cameras or sonar, which have negligible mea- denotedasxˆ andΣ respectively.Werefertotheeigenvalues
i i
surement time. Bishop, [11] directly evaluated the determi- of Σ as σ2(1) and σ2(2) for the larger and smaller at
i i i
nant of the FIM to find sufficient conditions for an optimal time-step i, respectively. For convenience of notation and
measurement sequence. But because the FIM is evaluated analysis, we specify sensing locations with respect to the
aroundthetruetargetlocation,whichisunknowninpractice, framedefinedbythemajorandminoraxisofthecovariance
this result cannot provide time-to-localize guarantees. ellipse. Let r and α be the distance and relative angle
i i
In our previous work, [12], we provided an algorithm between s and the major axis of the covariance ellipse Σ ,
i i
based on state-space enumerative search, and compared it i.e., the eigenvector corresponding to σ2(1).
i
directlytoaone-stepgreedyalgorithm.Bothalgorithmsused Theith bearingmeasurementisgivenbyz =h(x⋆,s )+
i i
the determinant of the posterior covariance but neither could n, where n (0,σ2) and h(a,b) = tan−1( by−ay).
provide a guarantee about final uncertainty. Furthermore, ∼ N s bx−ax
An Extended Kalman Filter (EKF) is used to update the
discretization and search over state space can be costly, and
target estimate. We use an EKF because of its closed-form
both were limited to a fixed-sized displacement between
representation and low demand on processing power. The
measurements. Finally, there was no systematic approach EKFupdateequationsforith measurementaregivenas[14]:
to the ambiguity of measurements. Instead, we implicitly
assumed the most likely measurement was correct. We
address each of these issues in this work: We derive a new xˆ i =xˆ i−1 +K i y i
greedystepwhichprovidesthenextmeasurementlocationin Σ =Σ Σ HTS−1H Σ .
closed-form. This removes the need for a state-space search. i i−1 − i−1 i i i i−1
We show how to select measurement locations to limit the (cid:0) (cid:1)
with:
effect of ambiguity, and bound the time spent by the robot
while providing a guarantee of posterior covariance.
The rest of the paper is organized as follows. In the 1
H = h(xˆ ,s )= sinα cosα
next section we provide a brief review of the necessary i ∇ xˆ i−1 i r − i i
i
background and notation. In Section III we show how S =H Σ HT +σ2 (cid:2) (cid:3)
i i i−1 i s
we can structure the measurement sequence to deal with K =Σ HTS−1
ambiguous measurements, and introduce our algorithm. In i i−1 i i
y =z h(xˆ,s )
Section IV, we provide a theoretical performance bound i i − i
on the algorithm. We evaluate the resulting algorithm in
simulation in Section V and we report on field trials of the
The EKF assumes p(z xˆ ) (h(xˆ ,s ),S ). In some
i i i i i
algorithm which demonstrate the feasibility for the intended | ∼ N
applications, particularly mobile target tracking, the equa-
application. Due to space limitations, we refer the reader to
tions for the EKF update include an additive noise term.
the technical report [13] for detailed proofs.
It is not included in our algorithm because we assume a
stationary target.
II. PROBLEMFORMULATION
AninversecovarianceformofEKFcalledExtendedInfor-
Our problem setup is shown in Figure 2. The goal is to
mation Filter (EIF) is defined for the same problem, but in a
localize a target, whose true position with respect to a fixed
global frame G is x⋆. The robot is initially located at formmore useful forour analysis: Σ− i 1 =Σ− i− 1 1 + σ 1 2 H i TH i .
{ } s
s . The robot moves to a location denoted by s to take We also use the fact that both the covariance matrix Σ−1
0 i
--- PAGE 3 ---
and HTH admit a unitary decomposition, which results in: Lettheprobabilitythatthetruetargetisbehindthesensor,
with respect to the target hypothesis be,
1 1
Σ− i 1 = R(θ i−1 ) · δ σ2 (1) , σ2 (2) · RT(θ i−1 ) p (s ,x⋆)=p y xˆ > π +p y xˆ < π (2)
(cid:20) i−1 i−1 (cid:21) b i i | i 2 i | i −2
+R(α +θ ) δ 0, 1 RT(α +θ ). Due to the Gaussia (cid:16) n prior, this (cid:17) proba (cid:16) bility is non-z (cid:17) ero for
i i−1 · r2σ2 · i i−1
(cid:20) i s(cid:21) any candidate sensor location. Therefore we define a risk
(1)
termβ andseekmeasurementlocationssuchthatp (s ,xˆ)<
b i
where R(θ) represents a 2-D rotation matrix with angle θ, β. If an algorithm can assure this for each measurement
x 0 location, we call it β-cautious. In [13] we prove that the
and δ[x,y] = is a diagonal matrix. Here, θ is the
0 y cautionconstraintprovidesanupperboundontheacceptable
orientation of t(cid:20)he cov(cid:21)ariance with respect to G. variance of y , given by σ , which constrains only the
i β
Lett m bethetimeittakestoobtainasinglemeasurement. rangeatwhichthesensorcantakemeasurements.Therange
Our objective is to find a set of measurement locations S = constraint is given by:
s ,s ,...,s which reduce both the eigenvalues of the
1 2 N
{ }
prior covariance (σ2(1),σ2(2)) by a given factor c2 < 1 in σ2(1) sin2α +σ2(2) cos2α
0 0 d r i · i i · i (3)
m
m
i
o
n
v
i
e
m
s
a
w
l
i
t
t
o
h
ta
u
l
n
t
i
i
t
m
v
e
e
,
lo
N
cit · y
t m
an
+
d c
t
a
t
n
. W
tu
e
rn
a
i
s
n
su
n
m
eg
e
li
t
g
h
i
a
b
t
le
th
t
e
im
ro
e.
bot i ≥s σ
β
2
−
σ
s
2
π
Hence our objective is: where σ = and φ() is the cumulative
β 2 φ−1(1 β) ·
minimize N t +D(S) Gaussian distributi·on. We a−ss 2 ume σ >σ . If this is not the
m β s
S={s1,...,sN} · case, intuitively, the sensor is too noisy to satisfy caution
subject to, σ (1) c σ (1), σ (2) c σ (2), and given the value of β assigned. In Section V we show that
N d 0 N d 0
≤ · ≤ ·
N 1, where D(S) is the total distance traveled by the reducing β arbitrarily drives the time spent by the algorithm
≥
robot for the given set of sensing locations. to infinity. This is because the required range r becomes
i
so great that the measurements have little effect on the
III. ACTIVELOCALIZATIONALGORITHM hypothesis. However, the number of measurements follows
We define a greedy algorithm which incorporates all prior in closed form (see Section IV), so the effect of β can be
information and outputs the next measurement location. At evaluated off-line.
each step, the input to our algorithm is the prior target
s
estimate (xˆ ,Σ ). The output of our algorithm is the i
i−1 i−1
N
locations fromwhichtherobotshouldobtainthenextmea-
i
surement. Measurement locations are chosen based on two
θ θ
factors.Weseekmeasurementlocationswhichcanminimize i+1 i
the largest eigenvector at each time step. This is subject to s
i+1 xˆ xˆ
a caution constraint, which represents the possibility of the i+1 i
target being behind the sensor.
To show the intuition for a cautious strategy, consider the
scenarioshowninFigure2.TheEKFpredictsmeasurements Fig. 3. One measurement step of the cautious strategy presented in
that correspond to the target hypothesis, xˆ , while the mea- Algorithm1.
i
surements are actually distributed around x⋆. If x⋆ is nearly
collinear with the sensor and hypothesis as shown, then the
Algorithm 1 β-Cautious Strategy(s ,xˆ ,Σ ,∆θ,β,σ2)
infinite line sensor is very likely to produce measurements 0 0 0 s
π
which show a low innovation. This is in direct conflict 1: σ2
with the true (but unknown) target location. In the update β ← 2 Φ−1(1 β)
· − 2
step of the EKF, we are forced to chose from the two 2: σ 0 2(1),σ 0 2(2) ← eigenvalues(Σ 0 )
possible measurements (zˆ which agrees with xˆ, or π+this 3: i 1
←
measurement) or maintain two hypotheses (one for each). 4: while σ i (1) c d σ 0 (1) or σ i (2) c d σ 0 (2) do
≥ · ≥ ·
According to the EKF, the lower probability measurement 5: Polar frame at xˆ i−1 aligned with σ i−1 (1)
(π I + ntu zˆ i ) ti i v s el a y c , tu th al i l s y s t i h tu e a c ti o o r n re o c c t c o u n r e s . when the angle between 6: r i ← σ σ i 2 β 2 − − 1( σ 1 s 2 )
z i ˆ s a b n e d hin z d ⋆ i t s he gr s e e a n t s e o r r. th O an r, π 2 if w y hic > h i π mp o l r ies y th < e true π, ta i r t ge is t 8 7 : : C Le o t ll s e i c r : t ( m r i e , a α su i ) re b m e e t n h t e z c i lo fr s o e m r o s f i (r i ,π 2 ) or ( − r i ,π 2 ).
likely that the target was beh i ind th 2 e sens i or. U − si 2 ng this 9: xˆ i ,Σ i ekf update(z i ,σ s ,xˆ i−1 ,Σ i−1 )
←
intuition, we can plan the measurement sequence to guard 10: σ i 2(1),σ i 2(2) ← eigenvalues(Σ i )
againstthispossibility,whichallowsustousethemostlikely 11: i i+1
←
measurement while limiting the possibility that this is the 12: end while
incorrect choice.
--- PAGE 4 ---
1000
800
600
400
200
0
−200
−400
−600
−800 −1000
−1200
−1000 −500 0 500 1000
X(m)
)m(Y
r 0
r 1
r t
2 1
r
3
ttt r tt567 8 88 r 7 tt r r 346 t 2 r 4 5
−500
−550
−600
−650
−700
−750
−800
−850
−900
−950
−1000
−300 −200 −100 0 100 200 300
X(m)
)m(Y
the two to save travel time.
Figure4showsacompletesimulatedrunofouralgorithm.
The robot travels in a zig-zag fashion towards target, and
after each measurement update, the target estimate shifts
(againinarectilinearsense)towardsthetruetargetlocation.
Becausethesensingrange,r monotonicallydecreases,we
i
expect that the time taken to travel to new sensing locations
would also decrease. We also expect the target estimate to
shift less with each successive measurement as the certainty
of the estimate increases. In the next section we use these intuitions to prove an upper bound on the time required to
localize the target.
IV. ANALYSIS
Our analysis proceeds in two parts: We first bound the
r
3 total time taken by the cautious algorithm, for a given input
instance. We call this T . We then derive a lower bound
ALG
on the time for any bearing-based localization strategy, not-
necessarily cautious, which we call T . We then take the
LB
expectation of these times with respect to the possible true
target locations, and show that the ratio is bounded above
tr tr
t5 6 8 r 7 t 3 46 t 2 r 4 by a constant. The main structural lemmas are stated here to
t 7 tt 88 provide intuition, but the proofs are deferred to [13].
Lemma 1: For the ith measurement if α = 0 or α =
r i i
5 π, then only one eigenvalue of the posterior covariance Σ
2 i
decreases, and the rotation of the posterior is the same as
the rotation of the prior.
Fig.4. Asimulationexecutionofthecautiousstrategy.Top:thefullrun. Lemma 2: For a given range from target, r , and an
i
Bottom:Detailoftheboxedregioninthefirstfigure.Reddenotesthefinal
eigenvalue we wish to reduce, a maximal reduction occurs
target, black is the true target, and green are the sensor locations. In this
example,therobotsuccessfullykeepsthetargethypothesisonthesameside when we set α i = π 2 with respect to the corresponding
asthetruetargetlocation,withnoknowledgeofthetruetarget. eigenvector.
Lemma 3: The maximum shift in target hypothesis is,
σ2
Algorithm 1 presents the details of our strategy and xˆ xˆ π i
Figure3showsameasurementstepofAlgorithm1inaction. || i − i−1 ||≤ σ r i i 2 +r i σ s 2
xˆ and Σ =δ(σ2 (1),σ2 (2)) is the estimate of the
i−1 i−1 i−1 i−1 where the measurement location was chosen according to
targetbeforetheith measurement.Recallthat(r ,α )arethe
i i Lemma 2.
polar coordinates in the frame of xˆ with the axis aligned
i−1
with the eigenvector corresponding to σ2 (1). Algorithm 1 A. Upper Bound on Algorithm Time
i−1
chooses the measurement location s :( σ1 2(i−1),π) . To derive T ALG We begin by proving a bound on the
i r σ β 2−σ s 2 2 number of measurements required for a given c d , then
After updating the target estimate using the EKF update show the sum of the distances between these measurement
equation with measured bearing z i , the target estimate shifts locations is bounded.
to a new location xˆ , σ2 (1) decreases, and σ2 (2) re- σ2
i i−1 i−1 Lemma 4: Define γ = β > 1. For a given acceptable
mains unchanged. The new measurement location is chosen σ2
s
p W e e rp s e h n o d w icu in la L r e t m o m th a e 1 ei t g h e e n c v o e v c a to ri r an c c o e rre m s a p t o r n ix di d n o g es to no σ t i 2 − ro 1 t ( a 2 te ). . risk parameter β, N z = ⌈ 4log γ c 1 d ⌉ measurements are
sufficient for the cautious strategy to achieve the given
(cid:16) (cid:17)
The robot then travels to this new location s (shown as
i+1 desired reduction c ,
a dashed line in Figure 3). d
Lemma 5: If Σ is circular, the total distance traveled by
0
This process continues until both the eigenvalues are
the robot during a complete execution of Algorithm 1 is
reduced by the desired factor. The algorithm is guaranteed
bounded i.e.,
to terminate since for every measurement steps, the larger
eigenvalue is guaranteed to decrease. In fact, we bound the 1 c
√2+πγ−1
D d(s ,s )+2σ (1) − d γ (4)
number of measurements taken by our strategy in Lemma 4. A ≤ 0 1 0 √γ 1 σ s √γ 1 !
− −
In practice, there are two candidate points which satisfy
the cautious requirement: at (r ,π) and reflected across the A natural extension shows that this is an upper-bound for
i 2
target eigenvector, at (r , π). We can chose the closer of the non-circular case. By combining Lemmas 4 and 5, we
i −2
--- PAGE 5 ---
can bound the total time spent by a cautious strategy, which Number of measurements vs β
25
holds for any problem instance.
Theorem 1: The total time spent by a β-cautious strategy
is bounded such that,
20
T N t +D (5)
ALG z m A
≤ ·
with constants N and D from Lemmas 4 and 5, respec- 15
z A
tively.
B. Lower Bound on Bearing-based Localization 10
We seek to bound the effect of ambiguity on the time to
localize a target. To do this, we derive T LB , a lower bound 5
on the time required to satisfy the same objectives for any
strategy, regardless of ambiguity. To eliminate the effect of
0
the prior estimate, we allow the LB strategy to have access 0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1
β
tothetruetargetlocation.Weanalyzeasimplifiedobjective:
Reduce only one eigenvalue by the required constant.
Lemma 6: Given an optimal measurement sequence S
O
for the one dimensional eigenvalue reduction problem there
exists a sequence S′, with measurements taken on a line
perpendicular to the eigenvector which takes no longer
to perform, and produces at least the same reduction in
uncertainty.
Lemma 7: Let S be an optimal measurement sequence
O
of size k measurements. Then a sequence S⋆ in which all
k measurements occur at the same point produces the same
change in eigenvalue in no worse time.
We combine these observations to produce a lower bound
on any not-necessarily cautious, optimal measurement se-
quence. We denote this sequence as S⋆, and its time cost as
T . LB
Theorem 2: Let S⋆ be the measurement sequence de-
scribedinLemma7.TheminimumtimetakenbyS⋆,which
is a lower bound for any strategy, is given by
σ2
T T(S⋆) max(r⋆ max +t ,t ) (6)
LB ≥ ≥ 0 − 2t (1 1)σ2 m m
m c2 − s
where σ = max(σ ,σ ), r⋆ is the range to the true max 1,0 2,0 0
target location at time 0, and r⋆ r⋆.
0 ≥ k
Letthesequenceofsensorlocationsgivenbyaβ-cautious
strategy be described by S with time cost T ( ) for a β ALG
X
specific problem setting . We can state the following.
X
Theorem 3: The cautious strategy is C-competitive.
Proof: We show:
E[T ( ))] C E[T ( ))] b
ALG LB
X − × X ≤
Where b does not depend on the input instance and E[] is
·
the expectation over x⋆ [13].
V. EVALUATION
In the previous section we reported the derivation of the
expected performance of the algorithm. In this section we
evaluatethisperformanceinavarietyofsimulationsandreal-
worldexperiments.Wefirstderivetheexpectedperformance
of our sensing platform as an example.
To detect tagged fish, we use a loop antenna and attached
radio receiver. A bearing measurement is constructed by
stnemerusaem
fo
rebmuN
Error vs β
800
700
600
500
400
300
200
100
0
0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1
β
sisehtopyh
ni
rorre
Fig.5. Simulationstudyoftheeffectofβ onnumberofmeasurements,
(top),andfinalaccuracy(bottom).Notethatasmallervalueofβ enforces
morecautioninthemeasurements.
sampling the RSSI as the antenna is rotated. This takes
approximately 1 minute due to the low duty cycle of the
radio tags. Since our robot travels at approximately 1 meter
per second, t 60. We have empirically estimated σ as
m s
≈ 15 degrees [12]. Supposing our initial hypothesis satisfies
σ (1) = σ (2) = 50 meters, and we begin our tracking at
0 0
r 60 meters, we can calculate the expected performance
0
≈ using (5). In this case, we find that N = 4 measurements
will be sufficient to reduce the one sigma bound to less than
6 meters. During this time we expect the robot to travel less
than 220 meters, resulting in a competitive ratio of less than
about 4.
A. Simulations
To gain further insight into the expected performance of
a β-cautious algorithm for various starting parameters, we
conducted simulation studies. We simulated a real-world
localizationscenariousingthenoiseandestimateuncertainty
we have encountered.
In Table I we show the results of approximating the
--- PAGE 6 ---
TABLEI
CFORVARIOUSALGORITHMPARAMETERS.
rˆ 0 c d tm β SimulatedRatio TheoreticalUpperBound
{20,50,200} .1 60 .10 {3.6366,2.8853,1.6651} {7.2853,5.4477,2.5477}
100 {.25.1.01} 60 .10 {1.3862,2.1418,2.8044} {2.2164,3.5869,4.9432}
100 .1 {20,60,110} .10 {1.6046,2.1398,2.5568} {2.3268,3.5869,4.5461}
100 .1 60 {.10,.2,.5} {2.6450,2.5699,1.5946} {3.9104,3.8353,2.2264}
True Target were required.
Final Estimate
s VI. CONCLUSION
s 1
0
We presented a novel variant of a greedy bearing-only
strategy,whichwecallcautious greedy.Wehaveshown that
acautiousstrategycanminimizetheeffectofambiguitywith
s s 4 an infinite line sensor. We then bounded the performance
2
of a cautious strategy, providing a worst-case guarantee on
s
3 the time taken by the algorithm. We have shown that the
expected performance times for real world applications is
often better than the theoretical result.
ACKNOWLEDGMENT
Fig.6. Asuccessfulfieldtrialofthecautiousalgorithm.Parametersforthis
trialwereσ β 2 =1andσ s 2=(cid:0)π 8(cid:1) 2 .The1σuncertaintyellipsesareshown This work is supported by NSF Awards #1111638,
for the prior and final estimates. The final error was less than 5 meters #0916209, #0917676, #0936710.
after only 4 measurements. The total experiment area was approximately
70metersby64meters. REFERENCES
[1] P. G. Bajer, C. J. Chizinski, and P. W. Sorensen, “Using the Judas
E[T ] technique to locate and remove wintertime aggregations of invasive
ratio C = ALG . The initial hypothesis was fixed with commoncarp,”FisheriesManagementandEcology,Oct.2011.
E[T LB ] [2] S.D.Bopardikar,“PursuitStrategiesforAutonomousVehicles,”Ph.D.
xˆ =(0,0) and σ (1)=σ (2)=60. We varied the starting dissertation,UniversityofCalifornia,SantaBarbara,2010.
0 0 0
parameters initial range rˆ , desired reduction c , caution [3] P. Tokekar, D. Bhadauria, A. Studenski, and V. Isler, “A Robotic
0 d System for Monitoring Carp in Minnesota Lakes,” Journal of Field
parameterβ,andmeasurementtimet .Truetargetlocations
m Robotics,vol.27,no.6,pp.779–789,2010.
were sampled with replacement from the target hypothesis, [4] N. Patwari, J. Ash, S. Kyperountas, A. Hero III, R. Moses, and
thecautiousalgorithmrun,andthemeanofdistancetraveled N. Correal, “Locating the nodes: cooperative localization in wireless
sensornetworks,”SignalProcessingMagazine,vol.22,no.4,pp.54–
andnumberofmeasurementswereusedtoestimatethereal-
69,2005.
world execution time. This was compared directly to the [5] J. Derenick, J. Fink, andV. Kumar,“Localization Using Ambiguous
predicted execution given by T from Theorem 2. Bearings from Radio Signal Strength,” in Proc. IEEE/RSJ Interna-
LB tionalConferenceonIntelligentRobotsandSystems. IEEE,2011.
InFigure5weshowtheeffectofintroducingβ-cautionto
[6] X.R.LiandV.P.Jilkov,“Surveyofmaneuveringtargettracking:III.
a greedy measurement strategy. Measurements were chosen Measurement models,” Proceedings of SPIE, vol. 4473, no. August,
to minimize the posterior uncertainty for a range of values pp.423–446,2001.
[7] ——, “Survey of maneuvering target tracking: I: dynamic models,”
of β. Each execution was terminated when it produced an
IEEE Transactions on Aerospace and Electronic Systems, vol. 39,
uncertainty with eigenvalues below some constant. From no.4,pp.1333–1364,Oct.2003.
thesewecanseethatacautiousstrategytendstoreducefinal [8] ——, “Survey of maneuvering target tracking: V: multiple-model
methods,” IEEE Transactions on Aerospace and Electronic Systems,
error (measured as xˆ x⋆ ), but excessively small values
vol.41,no.4,pp.1255–1321,Oct.2005.
|| − ||
of β can significantly increase the number of measurements [9] E. W. Frew, “Observer Trajectory Generation for Target-Motion
required. Estimation Using Monocular Vision,” Ph.D. dissertation, Stanford
University,2003.
[10] S. E. Hammel, P. T. Liu, E. J. Hilliard, and K. F. Gong, “Optimal
B. Field Experiments observer motion for localization with bearing measurements,” Com-
puters and Mathematics with Applications, vol. 18, no. 1-3, pp. 171
We also implemented the algorithm and tested it using
–180,1989.
a mobile chassis. The chassis is pictured in Figure 1. A [11] A. Bishop and P. Pathirana, “Optimal trajectories for homing nav-
transmitting radio tag was placed in a field measuring igation with bearing measurements,” in Proceedings of the 2008
InternationalFederationofAutomaticControlCongress,2008.
approximately 64 by 70 meters. Previously, we determined
[12] P. Tokekar, J. Vander Hook, and V. Isler, “Active target localization
this to be approximately the maximum detection distance forbearingbasedrobotictelemetry,”inProc.IEEE/RSJInternational
of our receiver. The robot was given a starting hypothesis ConferenceonIntelligentRobotsandSystems,2011.
[13] J. Vander Hook, P. Tokekar, and V. Isler, “Cautious greedy strategy
which encompassed the field. The starting parameters and
forbearing-basedactivelocalization:Technicalreport,”Universityof
performance closely match the parameters derived at the be- Minnesota,MN,USA,Tech.Rep.,2011.
ginning of this section. Specifically, the final covariance was [14] Y.Bar-Shalom,X.Li,andT.Kirubarajan,Estimationwithapplications
totrackingandnavigation. WileyInterScience,2001.
lessthan6meters,onesigmabound,andfourmeasurements
